So what makes a piece of music beautiful?
ما الذي يجعل الموسيقى جميلة؟
Well, most musicologists would argue
قد يجادل معظم علماء الموسيقى
that repetition is a key aspect of beauty,
بأن التكرار هو جانب أساسي في الجمال،
the idea that we take a melody, a motif, a musical idea,
فكرة أن نأخذ لحن، أو موضوع، أو فكرة موسيقية،
we repeat it, we set up the expectation for repetition,
فنكررها، ونتوقع التكرار،
and then we either realize it or we break the repetition.
ثم ندرك ذلك، أو نكسر التكرار.
And that's a key component of beauty.
وذلك مكون رئيسي للجمال.
So if repetition and patterns are key to beauty,
فإن كان التكرار والأنماط هي سر الجمال،
then what would the absence of patterns sound like,
فكيف سيبدو غياب الأنماط،
if we wrote a piece of music that had no repetition whatsoever in it?
إذا ألفنا مقطوعة موسيقية لا تحوي أي تكرار؟
That's actually an interesting mathematical question.
هذا السؤال الرياضي مثير للاهتمام.
Is it possible to write a piece of music that has no repetition whatsoever?
هل يمكن كتابة قطعة موسيقية لا تحوي أي تكرار؟
It's not random -- random is easy.
وليست عشوائية... فالعشوائية يسيرة.
Repetition-free, it turns out, is extremely difficult,
تبين أن عدم التكرار صعب للغاية،
and the only reason that we can actually do it
والسبب الذي يجعلنا قادرين على فعله
is because of a man who was hunting for submarines.
هو رجل كان يبحث عن الغواصات.
It turns out, a guy who was trying to develop the world's perfect sonar ping
اتضح أن رجلًا كان يحاول تطوير الرنين المثالي للسونار
solved the problem of writing pattern-free music.
قد حل مشكلة تأليف موسيقى خالية من التكرار.
And that's what the topic of the talk is today.
وذلك هو موضوع حديثنا اليوم.
So, recall that in sonar,
تذكروا أنه في السونار،
you have a ship that sends out some sound in the water,
لدينا سفينة ترسل صوتًا في الماء،
and it listens for it -- an echo.
ثم تستمع إلى تردده.
The sound goes down, it echoes back, it goes down, echoes back.
فالصوت يذهب إلى الأعماق ويرتد، ثم يذهب إلى الأعماق ويرتد.
The time it takes the sound to come back tells you how far away it is:
والوقت الذي يستغرقه الصوت ليرتد يخبرنا بالمسافة التي قطعها:
if it comes at a higher pitch,
فإن ارتد بنغمة أعلى،
it's because the thing is moving toward you;
فلأن الجسم يتحرك باتجاهك،
if it comes back at a lower pitch, it's moving away from you.
وإن ارتد بنغمة أقل، فهو يتحرك مبتعدّا.
So how would you design a perfect sonar ping?
لذا كيف نصمم نغمة السونار المثالية؟
Well, in the 1960s, a guy by the name of John Costas
في عام 1960، كان هناك شخص يدعى (جون كوستاس)
was working on the Navy's extremely expensive sonar system.
وكان يعمل على نظام سونار باهظ الثمن لدى البحرية.
It wasn't working, because the ping they were using was inappropriate.
ولم يكن يعمل لأن النغمة التي استخدموها لم تكن مناسبة.
It was a ping much like the following here.
كانت نغمة تشبه التالي هنا،
You can think of this as the notes and this is time.
هذا المحور يمثل النغمات وهذا يمثل الوقت.
(Piano notes play high to low)
(صوت نغمات بيانو عالية ثم منخفضة)
So that was the sonar ping they were using, a down chirp.
وكانت هذه هي نغمة السونار التي استخدموها، زقزقة منخفضة.
It turns out that's a really bad ping.
وتبين أن هذه النغمة رديئة للغاية.
Why? Because it looks like shifts of itself.
لماذا؟ لأنها تبدو مثل إزاحات من نفسها.
The relationship between the first two notes is the same as the second two,
فالعلاقة بين أول نغمتين مثل العلاقة بين ثانيهما،
and so forth.
وهكذا.
So he designed a different kind of sonar ping,
لذا صمم نوع مختلف من نغمات السونار،
one that looks random.
واحدة تبدو عشوائية.
These look like a random pattern of dots, but they're not.
هذه تبدو كشكل عشوائي من النقاط لكنها ليست كذلك.
If you look very carefully,
إن نظرتم بإمعان،
you may notice that, in fact, the relationship between each pair of dots
فربما تلاحظون أن العلاقة بين كل زوج من النقاط
is distinct.
فريدة.
Nothing is ever repeated.
فلا يوجد تكرار.
The first two notes and every other pair of notes
فأول نغمتين وكل زوج من النغمات
have a different relationship.
بينها علاقات مختلفة.
So the fact that we know about these patterns is unusual.
وحقيقة أننا نعلم عن هذه الأنماط غير اعتيادية.
John Costas is the inventor of these patterns.
وقد اخترع (جون كوستاس) هذه الأنماط.
This is a picture from 2006, shortly before his death.
هذه الصورة من عام 2006، قبل وفاته بوقت قليل.
He was the sonar engineer working for the Navy.
وكان مهندس السونار لدى البحرية.
He was thinking about these patterns,
كان يفكر في هذه الأنماط،
and he was, by hand, able to come up with them to size 12 --
وتمكن من صنعها بحجم 12
12 by 12.
12 في 12.
He couldn't go any further and thought maybe they don't exist
ولم يمكنه فعل أكثر من ذلك، وفكر أنه ربما هي غير موجودة
in any size bigger than 12.
بحجم أكبر من 12.
So he wrote a letter to the mathematician in the middle,
لذا كتب خطابًا إلى عالم الرياضيات في المنتصف،
a young mathematician in California at the time, Solomon Golomb.
وهو عالم رياضيات شاب في كاليفورنيا حينها، ويدعى (سولومون غولوم).
It turns out that Solomon Golomb
وتبين أن (سولومون غولوم)
was one of the most gifted discrete mathematicians of our time.
كان واحدًا من أكثر علماء الرياضيات موهبة في عصرنا.
John asked Solomon if he could tell him the right reference
وقد سأل (جون) (سولومون) عن مرجع مناسب
to where these patterns were.
عن هذه الأنماط.
There was no reference.
ولم يكن هناك مرجع.
Nobody had ever thought about a repetition,
فلم يسبق لأحد التفكير بالتكرار،
a pattern-free structure before.
وبنية خالية من الأنماط من قبل.
So, Solomon Golomb spent the summer thinking about the problem.
لذا أمضى (سولومون غولوم) الصيف مفكرًا في المشكلة.
And he relied on the mathematics of this gentleman here,
واعتمد على نظريات هذا الشخص هنا،
Évariste Galois.
(إيفاريست غالوا)
Now, Galois is a very famous mathematician.
و(غالوا) هو عالم رياضيات شهير.
He's famous because he invented a whole branch of mathematics
وهو شهير لأنه اخترع فرع كامل في الرياضيات
which bears his name, called Galois field theory.
والذي يحمل اسمه، ويدعى نظرية الحقل لغالوا.
It's the mathematics of prime numbers.
وهي رياضيات الأعداد الأولية.
He's also famous because of the way that he died.
وهو شهير أيضًا بسبب طريقة موته.
The story is that he stood up for the honor of a young woman.
والقصة هي أنه وقف مدافعًا عن شرف فتاة.
He was challenged to a duel, and he accepted.
وتم تحديه إلى مبارزة، وقد قبل.
And shortly before the duel occurred,
وقبل وقوع المبارزة،
he wrote down all of his mathematical ideas,
كتب كل أفكاره في الرياضيات،
sent letters to all of his friends, saying "Please, please" --
وأرسل خطابات إلى أصدقائه، قائلًا: "رجاءً"-
this was 200 years ago --
"رجاءً احرصوا على نشر هذه الأشياء في النهاية."
He then fought the duel, was shot and died at age 20.
ثم قاتل في المبارزة، وقتل وعمره 20 عامًا.
The mathematics that runs your cell phones, the internet,
الرياضيات التي يعمل بها هاتفك الخلوي، والإنترنت،
that allows us to communicate, DVDs,
وتمكننا من التواصل، وأقراص الفيديو الرقمية،
all comes from the mind of Évariste Galois,
جميعها نتجت من عقل (إيفارست غالوا)،
a mathematician who died 20 years young.
عالم رياضيات مات في العشرين من عمره.
When you talk about the legacy that you leave ...
عندما تتحدث عن الإرث الذي تتركه...
Of course, he couldn't have even anticipated
بالطبع هو لم يتوقع حتى
the way that his mathematics would be used.
كيف ستستخدم نظرياته.
Thankfully, his mathematics was eventually published.
ولحسن الحظ، تم نشر نظرياته في نهاية المطاف.
Solomon Golomb realized that that was exactly the mathematics needed
وقد أدرك (سولومون غولوم) أن هذه هي الرياضيات التي يحتاجها
to solve the problem of creating a pattern-free structure.
لحل مشكلة إنشاء بنية خالية من الأنماط.
So he sent a letter back to John saying,
لذا رد بخطاب على (جون) يقول فيه:
"It turns out you can generate these patterns using prime number theory."
"اتضح أنه يمكنك إنشاء هذه الأنماط باستخدام نظرية الأعداد الأولية."
And John went about and solved the sonar problem for the Navy.
وقام (جون) بحل مشكلة السونار للقوات البحرية.
So what do these patterns look like again?
فكيف تبدو هذه الأنماط مجددًا؟
Here's a pattern here.
هذا أحد الأنماط هنا.
This is an 88-by-88-sized Costas array.
هذه مصفوفة (كوستاس) بحجم 88 في 88.
It's generated in a very simple way.
وتم توليدها بطريقة بسيطة.
Elementary school mathematics is sufficient to solve this problem.
فرياضيات المرحلة الابتدائية كافية لحل هذه المشكلة.
It's generated by repeatedly multiplying by the number three:
وقد تم توليدها بالضرب المتكرر في الرقم ثلاثة:
1, 3, 9, 27, 81, 243 ...
1،3،9،27،81،243...
When I get to a number that's larger than 89 which happens to be prime,
عندما أحصل على رقم أكبر من 89 والذي يصادف أن يكون أوليًا،
I keep taking 89s away until I get back below.
احذف 89 حتى أحصل على قيم أقل.
And this will eventually fill the entire grid, 88 by 88.
وذلك سيملأ المصفوفة كاملة، 88 في 88.
There happen to be 88 notes on the piano.
وقد صدف وجود 88 نغمة في البيانو.
So today, we are going to have the world premiere
اليوم سيكون لدينا العرض الأول في العالم
of the world's first pattern-free piano sonata.
لأول لحن موسيقي خال من النمط.
So, back to the question of music:
وبالعودة إلى السؤال عن الموسيقى:
What makes music beautiful?
ما الذي يجعل الموسيقى جميلة؟
Let's think about one of the most beautiful pieces ever written,
دعونا نفكر في واحدة من أجمل المقطوعات التي كتبت،
Beethoven's Fifth Symphony and the famous "da na na na!" motif.
وهي السيمفونية الخامسة لـ(بتهوفن) واللحن "دا نا نا نا!"
That motif occurs hundreds of times in the symphony --
وهو اللحن الذي يتكرر مئات المرات في السيمفونية...
hundreds of times in the first movement alone
مئات المرات في الحركة الأولى وحدها
and also in all the other movements as well.
ومئات المرات في الحركات الأخرى أيضًا.
So the setting up of this repetition is so important for beauty.
لذا فإن إعداد هذا التكرار مهم جدًا للجمال.
If we think about random music as being just random notes here,
إذا فكرنا في الموسيقى العشوائية كمجرد نقاط عشوائية هنا،
and over here, somehow, Beethoven's Fifth in some kind of pattern,
وهنا، يوجد السيمفونية الخامسة لـ(بتهوفن) بنمطيتها،
if we wrote completely pattern-free music,
إذا كتبنا موسيقى خالية تمامًا من الأنماط،
it would be way out on the tail.
فستكون في المؤخرة.
In fact, the end of the tail of music would be these pattern-free structures.
في الواقع، إن أسوأ موسيقى هي ذات البنية الخالية من الأنماط.
This music that we saw before, those stars on the grid,
هذه الموسيقى التي رأيناها سابقًا، هذه النجوم على الشبكة،
is far, far, far from random.
بعيدة تمامًا عن العشوائية.
It's perfectly pattern-free.
إنها خالية تمامًا من الأنماط.
It turns out that musicologists --
وتبين أن عالم موسيقى...
a famous composer by the name of Arnold Schoenberg --
وهو مؤلف مشهور باسم (آرنولد شونبرج)...
thought of this in the 1930s, '40s and '50s.
فكر في الأمر في ثلاثينات وأربعينات وخمسينات القرن العشرين.
His goal as a composer was to write music
وكان هدفه كمؤلف هو تأليف موسيقى
that would free music from tonal structure.
تحرر الموسيقى من البنية النغمية.
He called it the "emancipation of the dissonance."
وسماها "التحرر من التنافر."
He created these structures called "tone rows."
وأنشأ هذه البنيات المسماة "صفوف النغمات."
This is a tone row there.
هذا صف نغمات هناك.
It sounds a lot like a Costas array.
وهي تبدو مثل مصفوفة (كوستاس) كثيرًا.
Unfortunately, he died 10 years before Costas solved the problem
وللأسف مات منذ 10 سنوات، قبل أن يحل (كوستاس) مشكلة
of how you can mathematically create these structures.
كيفية إنشاء هذه البنية رياضيًا.
Today, we're going to hear the world premiere of the perfect ping.
اليوم سنسمع العرض الأول في العالم للرنين المثالي.
This is an 88-by-88-sized Costas array,
هذه هي مصفوفة (كوستاس) بحجم 88 في 88،
mapped to notes on the piano,
في شكل نغمات بيانو،
played using a structure called a Golomb ruler for the rhythm,
تعزف باستخدام بنية تدعى مسطرة (غولوم) للإيقاع،
which means the starting time of each pair of notes
وهي تعني أن وقت بدء كل زوج من النغمات
is distinct as well.
فريد أيضًا.
This is mathematically almost impossible.
وهذا الأمر مستحيل تقريبًا رياضيًا.
Actually, computationally, it would be impossible to create.
في الواقع، يستحيل حسابيًا إنشاؤها.
Because of the mathematics that was developed 200 years ago,
وبسبب الرياضيات التي تم تطويرها قبل 200 عام،
through another mathematician recently and an engineer,
وبواسطة عالم رياضيات آخر ومهندس،
we were able to actually compose this, or construct this,
كان بإمكاننا تكوين هذا البناء،
using multiplication by the number three.
باستخدام مضروب الرقم ثلاثة.
The point when you hear this music
وعندما تسمعون هذه الموسيقى
is not that it's supposed to be beautiful.
فليس المقصود أن تبدو جميلة.
This is supposed to be the world's ugliest piece of music.
فهذه هي أسوأ قطعة موسيقية بالعالم.
In fact, it's music that only a mathematician could write.
في الواقع هي موسيقى لا يكتبها إلا عالم رياضيات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When you're listening to this piece of music, I implore you:
أرجو منكم عند سماع هذه الموسيقى:
try and find some repetition.
حاولوا البحث عن تكرار.
Try and find something that you enjoy,
حاولوا البحث عن شيء ممتع،
and then revel in the fact that you won't find it.
ثم امرحوا لحقيقة أنكم لم تجدوه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So without further ado, Michael Linville,
لذا، وبدون مزيد من المقدمات، سيقوم (مايكل لينفيل)،
the [Dean] of Chamber Music at the New World Symphony,
عميد موسيقى الغرفة في أكاديمية سيمفونية العالم الجديد،
will perform the world premiere of the perfect ping.
بأداء العرض الأول للرنين المثالي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Music ends)
(نهاية الموسيقى)
(Scott Rickard, off-screen) Thank you.
(سكوت ريكارد) شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)